hey everyone, it's professor Dave, I want to tell you some things about ozonolysis.
ozonolysis is a reaction that utilizes ozone as a reagent
ozone is a triatomic allotrope of oxygen that exists as a zwitterion
that's ozone, that's the stuff up in the atmosphere
ozonolysis utilizes an alkene substrate and what happens is that this double bond
gets cleaved and pulled apart, and each of the carbons that was participating in the double bond
is now a carbonyl.
so this is useful for transforming alkenes into ketones and aldehydes.
we won't look at the mechanism here, but that is available on the internet for you to take a look at
it's a little bit interesting to look at
the reason this is a very useful reaction is that we can do some things like transforming
terminal alkenes into aldehydes which is something that can be very useful for synthesis
so basically any time you are looking at an ozonolysis reaction, remember that we are cleaving
that double bond and pulling apart the fragments and on each of the carbons that was participating
in the double bond, we will place an oxygen atom, and it will be in the form of a carbonyl
here we are generating this aldehyde and formaldehyde
which can easily be separated, we've changed the functionality of a part of this molecule
which may be useful for the next step in a synthesis
the other thing that's interesting about ozonolysis is if you perform ozonolysis on a cyclic alkene
you won't then get two molecules, you will simply pull apart that ring and get one linear product
this is useful to number sometimes when we have cyclic structures like this
we want to take these seven carbons
it's very easy to draw an incorrect product if we don't do something like numbering the carbons
what this is going to do for us is show that if we cleave this double bond and pull that molecule apart
we know that the resulting carbonyls when we draw the linear product must be on carbons 2 and 7
because those were the carbons that were participating in the double bond
that's just a trick to help you draw the correct ozonolysis product.
thanks for watching, guys. subscribe to my channel for more tutorials
and as always feel free to email me with questions